Guide to the Edwin Hale Abbot Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edwin Hale Abbot family papers
1787-1933
MS 27
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
51.5
The papers contain correspondence, letterpress copybooks, legal and financial documents, diaries, maps, blueprints, and photographs, the bulk of which documents the personal life and law and business careers of Edwin Hale Abbot.
Abbot, Edwin Hale, 1834-1927
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1957 from Edward Merrill & Son.
Arrangement
Arranged in ten series and one addition: I. General Correspondence, 1847-1933. II. Letterpress Copybooks, 1856-1917. III. Business Papers, 1787-1933. IV. Volumes, 1836-1915. V. Maps, Blueprints, and Drawings, 1828-1929. VI. Financial and Legal Papers, 1833-1928. VII. Photographs, 1845-1914. VIII. Phillips Brooks House, 1890-1910. IX. Memorabilia and Personal Papers, 1861-1894. X. Oversize, 1808-1931.
Scope and Contents
The Edwin Hale Abbot Family papers contain correspondence, letterpress copybooks, legal and financial documents, diaries, maps, blueprints, and photographs, the bulk of which documents the personal life, law and business careers of Edwin Hale Abbot.
Correspondence, diaries, legal and financial documents and photographs document the social and family business activities of members of Abbot and his immediate and extended family. Personal records of non-family members for whom Abbot acted as estate executor are contained in the papers. Of particular note are Edwin Hale Abbot's diaries and correspondence from his years at Harvard and correspondence between Edward Stanley Abbot and family and friends during his Civil War duty as a Union soldier before his death at Gettsburg.
Edwin Hale Abbot's professional career is documented in correspondence, letterpress copybooks, legal and financial documents, minutes of meetings, maps, architectural drawings, and photographs. The bulk of these materials are the records of the railroad, mining, real estate and other companies in which Abbot was actively involved. These include the Wisconsin Central Railroad, the Wisconsin Car Company, the Chicago and Great Western Railroad, the Chicago, Wisconsin and Minnesota Railroad, the Foreign McKenna Process Company, and others. The materials also document the development of the midwestern United States (particularly Chicago and Milwaukee) and the method of construction and operation of various railroads from 1870 to 1904. Maps, blueprints and photographs of rail lines, railroad stations, mines and steel mills provide visual documentation.
The material was purchased in 1957 from Edward Morril and Son. The 49.5 linear feet of papers are arranged by type and form of material in ten series.
Series I: The chronologically arranged GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE (1847-1933) relates to personal and business matters of Edwin Hale Abbot and his immediate and extended family. The bulk of the personal correspondence dates to 1870 and includes letters sent and received by Edwin Hale Abbot, Mary Carter Abbot, Edward Stanley Abbot, Martha Steele Abbot, Henry Larcom Abbot, Abby Steele and other family members and friends. After 1870 letters relating to Edwin Hale Abbot's law and business interests dominate the correspondence. Correspondence dated after 1927 relates to Edwin Hale Abbot Jr.'s business activities.
Series II: LETTERPRESS COPYBOOKS (1856-1917) is arranged alphabetically by individual or company name. The bulk of the copybooks relates to the Wisconsin Central Railroad and associated lines. Planning, construction and administration of the railroads is documented in the copybooks which were maintained by Abbot and other company administrators.
Series III: BUSINESS PAPERS (1787-1933) consists of legal and financial documents which are arranged chronologically. Documents dating from 1787-1870 relate to Abbot, Larcom and Steele family business and consist primarily of land deeds, insurance policies and wills. Financial and legal records document Edwin Hale Abbot's early law career. The bulk of the material dating from 1870-1933 relates to the railroad, mining, property and steel concerns of Edwin Hale Abbot, and consists of annual reports, legal proceedings, and financial reports.
Series IV: VOLUMES (1836-1915) contains a variety of types of bound documents, the bulk of which relates to the business and personal interests of Edwin Hale Abbot. This series is arranged in three subseries: Railroads, Mines and Businesses, Legal Cases, and Personal Records.
Railroads, Mines and Businesses is arranged by size (general and over-size) and contains cash books, day books, financial ledgers, minutes of meetings, stock certificates, stock ledgers, and other bound documents relating to Edwin Hale Abbot's business interests. Particularly well represented are the Wisconsin Central Railroad and its associated lines, the American McKenna Process Company, and the English McKenna Process Company. A scrapbook containing clippings from New York, Boston, Milwaukee and other cities documents the activities of Abbot and his railroad business associates from 1885-1887.
Legal Cases contains transcripts of legal proceedings and materials relating to civil suits in which Abbot was involved personally (as an attorney) or corporately. The materials are arranged alphabetically by name of plaintiff.
Personal Records consists of diaries, account, bank, and cash books and other materials of Edwin Hale Abbot, members of his family and business associates which are arranged alphabetically by name.
Series V: MAPS, BLUEPRINTS, AND DRAWINGS (1828-1929) is arranged in three subseries: Railroads, Mines, and Businesses, Regions and Personal Property and Miscellaneous.
The bulk of material in the subseries Railroads, Mines, and Businesses consists of blueprints and drawings of railyards, railroad stations and mining sites which are arranged alphabetically by company name.
Regions contains maps of Wisconsin, Michigan, Washington, and other states, many of which denote rail lines. These are arranged alphabetically by state.
Personal Property and Miscellaneous contains maps and drawings of property owned by the Abbot and Steele families. Civil War maps of the South with a letter from General Samuel Cooper to the Confederate War Department are also contained within this subseries.
Series VI: FINANCIAL AND LEGAL PAPERS (1833-1928) is arranged in two subseries: Railroads, Mines, and Businesses and Personal Records.
Railroads, Mines, and Businesses includes company financial reports, articles of agreement, and stock and bond certificates which are arranged by company name.
Personal Records consists of insurance certificates and Harvard College bills of Edwin Hale Abbot, and correspondence, legal documents, and wills relating to Abbot, Steele and Carter family property in Massachusetts and Maine. This material is arranged by name and type of material.
Series VII: PHOTOGRAPHS (1845-1914) is arranged in two subseries: Railroads and Businesses and Family and Miscellanea.
Railroads and Businesses contains photo prints relating to the construction of the Grand Central Passenger railroad station in Chicago, the Manitowoc Wisconsin terminal yard and harbor, rail lines in Wisconsin, and to activities of other businesses.
Family and Miscellanea contains photograph albums and loose photo prints of members of the Abbot family and others. A guide to a series of numbered photographs and genealogical notes provides detailed descriptions of Abbot family members, homes, and properties. Both the guide and the majority of numbered photographs are undated, however. Five folders of undated miscellaneous and unidentified individuals and locations are contained within this subseries.
Series VIII: PHILLIPS BROOKS HOUSE (1890-1910). The bulk of this series consists of the chronologically arranged correspondence of Edwin Hale Abbot relating to the fund drive and dedication ceremony for the Phillips Brooks House at Harvard.
Series IX: MEMORABILIA AND PERSONAL PAPERS (1861-1894) contains railroad passes and tickets, greeting cards and two literary productions: a poem, "Ne-Con-Dis" (1894), and an undated typescript, "Joseph Hale Abbot, 1802-1873" by William F. Abbot which contains copies of correspondence and biographical notes of Joseph Hale Abbot.
Series X: OVERSIZE (1808-1931) is arranged in two subseries: Maps, Blueprints and Drawings and Financial and Legal Papers.
Maps, Blueprints, and Drawings contains materials relating to railroad and mining companies. One folder (767) contains photographs and financial and legal papers relating to the Colby and Abbot building in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
Financial and Legal Papers contains documents relating to railroads, mines and businesses, and personal records (insurance policies, passports, property records) of Abbot family members and Charles L. Colby and Gardner Colby. The materials are arranged by personal name and type of document.
Biographical / Historical
Edwin Hale Abbot was born in Beverly, Massachusetts, in 1834, the son of Joseph Hale and Frances Ellingwood Larcom Abbot, and brother of Henry Larcom, Francis Ellingwood and Edward Stanley Abbot. He was educated at the Boston Latin School (1846-1851) and Harvard, where he was secretary of his class and where he received the A.B. (1855), the A.M. (1858), and the LL.B. (1862). In 1859 Abbot married Mary Carter, who died the following year. His marriage to Martha T. Steele in 1866 produced two sons, Philip Stanley and Edwin Hale, Jr., and an adopted daughter, Constance.
Abbot practiced law in Boston from 1862 to 1876. After 1876 railroad and corporate litigation and affairs in the midwestern United States dominated his legal practice. From 1873, when he became general solicitor for the Wisconsin Central Railroad, until 1909 when he retired as President of the Wisconsin Central Company, Abbot was instrumental in the development of railroad lines, terminals, and mines in Wisconsin, Illinois, Michigan, and Minnesota. Much of this development centered in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, where the Wisconsin Central Company was based. He was responsible for construction of the Grand Central Station and terminal in Chicago, the establishment of the first car-ferry for entire trains across Lake Michigan, and the uniting of all Wisconsin Central railroads into one company. His Wisconsin Central Plan (1879), by which control of the corporation was vested in bondholders through reservation to them of voting power on stock, had a major impact on subsequent corporate organization theory and practice.
In addition, Abbot was president of the Central Car Company, the Milwaukee Property Company, and the Foreign McKenna Process Company, a division of the American McKenna Process Company.
Abbot's business associates included John Lathrop, Leonard A. Jones, Charles L. Colby, Gardner Colby, William Wallace Crapo, Henry F. Spencer, Frederick Abbot, Frederick Weil, and his sons Philip Stanley and Edwin Hale Abbot, Jr.
Law editor of the Boston Daily Advertiser from 1862 until 1870, Abbot was also a contributor to the North American Review, the New Jerusalem Magazine, and the American Law Review. He wrote two works, A Review of the Report Upon the Physics and Hydraulics of the Mississippi (1862) and Phillips Brooks House (1900). He lectured at Harvard College, the University of Chicago, the University of Wisconsin, and other educational institutions.
With the exception of a number of years as a resident of Milwaukee, Wisconsin (c. 1876), Abbot lived his adult life in Cambridge, Massachusetts. He died in 1927.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Other Finding Aids
For a partial listing of the outgoing correspondence of Edwin Hale Abbot, please consult the Correspondence Index.
Corporation law -- United States; Families -- New England; Railroads -- Illinois; Railroads -- Minnesota; Railroads -- Wisconsin; Middle West; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Industries -- United States; Account books; Diaries; Journals (notebooks); Maps -- Middle West; Photoprints; Capitalists and financiers; Lawyers; Abbot, Edward Stanley, 1841-1863; Abbot, Edwin Hale, 1834-1927; Abbot, Edwin Hale, 1834-1927; Abbot, Francis Ellingwood, 1836-1903; Abbot, Henry L.; Abbot, Jos. Hale (Joseph Hale), 1802-1873; Abbot, Martha T. Steele; Abbot, Mary Carter; Abbot, Philip Stanley, 1867-1896; Brooks, Phillips, 1835-1893; Colby, Charles L.; Colby, Gardner, 1810-1879; Crapo, William Wallace, 1830-1926; Jones, Leonard A. (Leonard Augustus), 1832-1909; Lathrop, John, 1835-1910; Spencer, Henry F.; Weil, Frederick; American McKenna Process Co; English McKenna Process Co; Harvard University ( Students); Wisconsin Central Railroad Company (1871-1899)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1847-1933; Series I; 5.5' (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged chronologically.
  - 1847 - 1859 July (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - 1859 August - 1862 (Box 2, Folder 10-16)
  - 1863 - 1868 (Box 3, Folder 17-23)
  - 1869 - 1872 August (Box 4, Folder 24-31)
  - 1872 September - 1883 (Box 5, Folder 32-42)
  - 1884 - 1891 January (Box 6, Folder 43-49)
  - 1891 February - 1894 (Box 7, Folder 50-59)
  - 1895 - 1897 May (Box 8, Folder 60-75)
  - 1897 June - 1899 March (Box 9, Folder 76-94)
  - 1899 April - 1902 December (Box 10, Folder 95-112)
  - 1903 February - 1917 December (Box 11, Folder 113-127)
  - 1918 - 1933 (Box 12, Folder 128-137)
  - Undated (Box 13, Folder 138-141)
- LETTERPRESS COPYBOOKS, 1856-1917; Series II; 6' (17 boxes)
  This series contains material arranged chronologically within alphabetized subject files.
  - Abbot, Edwin Hale
    - 1857-1875 (Box 14, Folder 142-144)
    - 1865-1874 (Box 15, Folder 145-146)
    - 1866-1885 (Box 16, Folder 147-149a)
  - Abbot, Philip Stanley, 1895-1896 (Box 17, Folder 150)
  - Abbot and Jones
    - 1867-1872 (Box 17, Folder 151-152)
    - 1870-1871 (Box 18, Folder 153)
    - 1871-1874 (Box 19, Folder 154-155)
  - American McKenna Process Company, 1901-1917 (Box 20, Folder 156)
  - Central Car Company
    - 1886-1892 (Box 20, Folder 157)
    - 1891-1900 (Box 21, Folder 158)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 22, Folder 159)
  - Chicago and Great Western Railroad
    - 1886-1887 (Box 23, Folder 160-163)
    - 1887-1889 (Box 24, Folder 164-166)
  - St. Paul and St. Croix Railroad and St. Croix and Chippewa Falls Railroad, 1884-1885 (Box 25, Folder 167-169)
  - Wisconsin and Minnesota Railroad, 1880-1884 (Box 26, Folder 170)
  - Wisconsin Central Companies
    - 1889-1895 (Box 27, Folder 171-173)
    - 1893-1898 (Box 28, Folder 174-175)
  - Wisconsin Central Lines, 1886-1887 (Box 29, Folder 176)
  - Wisconsin Central Railroad
    - 1880-1881 (Box 30, Folder 177-178)
  - No folder (Box 30, Folder 179)
- BUSINESS PAPERS, 1787-1933; Series III; 9' (22 boxes)
  - 1787 - 1859 (Box 31, Folder 180-188)
  - 1860 - 1871 (Box 32, Folder 189-196)
  - 1872 - 1875 (Box 33, Folder 197-203)
  - 1876 - 1879 (Box 34, Folder 204-211)
  - 1880-1882 (Box 35, Folder 212-219)
  - 1883-1886 August (Box 36, Folder 220-227)
  - 1886 September-1887 (Box 37, Folder 228-235)
  - 1888-1889 September (Box 38, Folder 236-242)
  - 1889 October-1891 (Box 39, Folder 243-248)
  - 1892-1894 May 21 (Box 40, Folder 249-257)
  - 1894 May 22 - 1895 June (Box 41, Folder 258-264)
  - 1895 July - 1896 May (Box 42, Folder 265-270)
  - 1896 June - 1897 August (Box 43, Folder 271-277)
  - 1897 September - 1898 August (Box 44, Folder 278-283)
  - 1898 September - 1899 (Box 45, Folder 284-294)
  - 1900-1903 July (Box 46, Folder 295-305)
  - 1903 August - 1905 (Box 47, Folder 306-318)
  - 1906 - 1910 (Box 48, Folder 319-328)
  - 1911 - 1925 (Box 49, Folder 329-336)
  - 1926 - 1931 June (Box 50, Folder 337-345)
  - 1931 July-1933, undated (Box 51, Folder 346-355)
  - undated (Box 52, Folder 356-365)
- VOLUMES, 1836-1915; Series IV; 15' (55 boxes)
  This series contains general and oversize material arranged alphabetically by company or personal name within three subseries: Railroads, Mines, and Businesses, Legal Cases and Personal Records.
  - Railroads, Mines, and Businesses
    - General
      - Abbot & Hayes, Agents
        - Cash book: gold mine and ranch, 1896 (Box 53, Folder 366)
      - Abbot & Jones
        - Cash book, 1867-1871 (Box 53, Folder 367)
        - Day book, 1867-1872 (Box 53, Folder 368)
        - Index, "Finished Papers", 1867, undated (Box 53, Folder 369)
        - Journal, 1873 (Box 53, Folder 370)
        - Records of Boston estates, Circa 1868-1873 (Box 54, Folder 371-373)
      - Ashland Iron Mining Company
        - Stock ledger, 1884-1887 (Box 55, Folder 374)
      - Central Car Company
        - Minutes, 1879-1899 (Box 55, Folder 375-377)
      - Chicago & Great Western Railroad Company
        - Minutes, 1867-1885 (Box 55, Folder 378)
        - Minutes and maps, 1889 (Box 55, Folder 379)
        - Minutes and maps, 1889 (Box 56, Folder 380)
        - Stock certificates, 1884-1885 (Box 56, Folder 381)
      - Chicago and Northern Pacific Railroad Company and Chicago and Calumet Terminal Railway Company
        - Charters, ordinances, and other documents, 1892 (Box 56, Folder 382)
      - Chicago South Branch Dock Company
        - Stock certificates, 1887 (Box 56, Folder 383)
        - Stock ledger, 1871-1887 (Box 56, Folder 384)
      - Chicago, Wisconsin and Minnesota Railroad Company
        - Auditor's statements, 1887-1888 (Box 57, Folder 385)
        - Cash book and journal, 1890-1899 (Box 57, Folder 386)
        - Minutes, 1892-1899 (Box 57, Folder 387)
        - Stock ledger, 1886-1892 (Box 57, Folder 388)
        - Stock transfers, 1886 (Box 57, Folder 389)
      - Colby, Abbot & Hoyt, Trustees
        - Cash book: "Chicago Account", 1885-1889 (Box 58, Folder 390)
        - Cash book: Wisconsin Central Company, 1887-1890 (Box 58, Folder 391)
        - Journal, 1885-1889 (Box 58, Folder 392)
        - Journal: for Wisconsin Central Company, 1888-1891 (Box 58, Folder 393)
        - Ledger, 1885-1889 (Box 58, Folder 394)
        - Ledger: Wisconsin Central Company, 1887-1891 (Box 59, Folder 395)
        - Mortgage notes: Grand Central Passenger Station (Chicago), Chicago & Great Western Railroad Company, 1888-1890 (Box 59, Folder 396)
        - Stock ledger: Chicago & Great Western Railroad Company, 1885-1886 (Box 59, Folder 397)
        - Stock ledger: Chicago, Wisconsin and Minnesota Railroad Company, 1886 (Box 59, Folder 398)
      - Colby, Finney & Company
        - Account book, 1888-1890 (Box 59, Folder 399)
      - English McKenna Process Company
        - Articles of association, 1903 (Box 60, Folder 400)
        - Cash book, 1904-1908 (Box 60, Folder 401)
        - Journal, 1904-1908 (Box 60, Folder 402)
        - Ledger, 1904-1908 (Box 60, Folder 403)
        - Notes registers, 1909-1911 (Box 60, Folder 404)
        - Receipts: trustee-certificates, 1903-1905 (Box 61, Folder 405)
        - Report: mill sites, 1902 (Box 61, Folder 406)
        - Scrip-certificates, 1905-1908 (Box 61, Folder 407)
        - Stock registers, 1905-1910 (Box 61, Folder 408-409)
        - Vouchers, 1903-1909 (Box 62, Folder 410-411)
      - Hoosac Quarry Company
        - Stock ledger, 1872 (Box 62, Folder 412)
      - Lake Washington Belt Line Company
        - Journal, 1909-1912 (Box 62, Folder 413)
      - Lathrop, Abbot & Jones
        - Cash book, 1870-1874 (Box 63, Folder 414)
        - Journals, 1870-1874 (Box 63, Folder 415-416)
        - Ledger, 1870-1874 (Box 64, Folder 417)
      - Manitowoc and Minnesota Railroad Company
        - Minutes, 1868-1871 (Box 64, Folder 418)
      - Milwaukee & Lake Winnebagon Railroad Company
        - Cash book and journal, 1890-1899 (Box 64, Folder 419)
        - Construction accounts: Manitowoc Division
          - Journal, 1896-1897 (Box 64, Folder 420)
          - Ledger, 1896-1897 (Box 65, Folder 421)
        - Journal, 1882-1893 (Box 65, Folder 422)
        - Minutes, 1892-1898 (Box 65, Folder 423)
        - Stock certificates, 1896 (Box 65, Folder 424)
      - Minnesota, St. Croix and Wisconsin Railroad Company
        - Auditor's statements, 1885-1888 (Box 65, Folder 425)
        - Contracts, 1884 (Box 66, Folder 426)
        - Journal, 1884-1890 (Box 66, Folder 427)
        - Ledger, with correspondence, 1884-1890 (Box 66, Folder 128)
        - List of bonds, 1884-1885 (Box 66, Folder 429)
      - Penokee & Gogebic Development Company
        - Stock transfers, 1884-1887 (Box 66, Folder 430)
      - Penokee Railroad Company
        - Auditor's statements, 1887-1888 (Box 66, Folder 431)
      - Phillips & Colby Construction Company
        - Stock ledger, 1878 (Box 66, Folder 432)
      - Portage, Winnebago and Superior Railroad Company (Box 67, Folder 433)
        - Legal Records (Box 67, Folder 433)
        - Minutes, 1869-1876 (Box 67, Folder 433a-435)
      - Shea and George Dock Company
        - Minutes, 1882-1890 (Box 68, Folder 436)
      - Stewart & Abbot, Collateral Trustees: Wisconsin Central Company
        - Cash book and journal, 1893-1899 (Box 68, Folder 437)
        - Ledger, 1893-1899 (Box 68, Folder 438)
        - Minutes, 1892-1899 (Box 68, Folder 439)
        - Minutes, 1894-1898 (Box 69, Folder 440)
      - Stewart & Abbot, Trustees
        - Bank book: Wisconsin Central Railroad Company Sinking Fund, 1900-1902 (Box 69, Folder 441)
      - [Western States Construction Company?]
        - Journal, 1884-1885 (Box 69, Folder 442)
        - Ledger, 1884-1885 (Box 69, Folder 443)
      - Wisconsin and Minnesota Railroad Company
        - Auditor's statements, 1880-1888 (Box 70, Folder 444-445)
        - Stock transfers, 1885-1887 (Box 70, Folder 446)
      - Wisconsin Central Associated Lines
        - Auditor's statements, 1886-1887 (Box 70, Folder 447)
        - Auditor's statements, 1887-1888 (Box 71, Folder 448)
      - Wisconsin Central Company
        - Trial balances, 1894-1898 (Box 71, Folder 449)
      - Wisconsin Central Company and Wisconsin Central Railroad Company
        - Improvement bonds: journal, 1891 (Box 71, Folder 450)
        - Improvement bonds: ledger, 1891 (Box 71, Folder 451)
        - Improvement bonds: minutes, 1897-1899 (Box 72, Folder 452)
        - Physical record, 1890 (Box 72, Folder 453)
      - Wisconsin Central Railroad Company
        - Cash book and journal, 1890-1893 (Box 72, Folder 454)
        - Reorganization bonds settlement schedule, 1879-1881 (Box 72, Folder 455)
        - Reorganization settlements, 1879 (Box 73, Folder 456)
        - Warrant certificate register, 1875-1877 (Box 73, Folder 457)
      - [Wisconsin Central Railroad Company?]
        - [Reorganization settlements ledger?], undated (Box 73, Folder 458)
      - Wisconsin Central Railroad Company and Milwaukee & Lake Winnebago Railroad Company
        - Auditor's statements, 1884-1888 (Box 73, Folder 459)
      - Wisconsin Central Railroad Company and Milwaukee and Northern Railroad Company
        - Auditor's statements of earnings, 1878-1884 (Box 74, Folder 460)
      - Wisconsin Central Receivers
        - Cash book, 1893-1898 (Box 74, Folder 461)
      - Various railroads (especially Wisconsin Central Company)
        - Accounts and trial balances, 1882-1888 (Box 74, Folder 462)
        - Accounts and trial balances, 1888-1898 (Box 75, Folder 463-465)
        - Accounts and trial balances, 1897-1899 (Box 76, Folder 466)
        - Scrapbook: newspaper clippings, 1885-1887 (Box 76, Folder 467)
      - Various interests
        - Abstracts of land titles, 1884 (Box 77, Folder 468-470)
        - Cash and trusts book, 1875-1878 (Box 77, Folder 471)
        - Cash books, 1875-1878, 1889 (Box 77, Folder 472-473)
        - Journal, 1872 (Box 78, Folder 474)
        - Ledgers, 1863-1871, 1875 (Box 78, Folder 475-478)
      - Unidentified
        - Stock certificate register, 1884-1885 (Box 78, Folder 479)
    - Oversize
      - American McKenna Process Company